Why do you want to get rid of birthright citizenship?
And how, by the way?
Because you know it's in the Constitution.
I'm so glad you brought this up.
Yes.
Because it was one of my-
The 14th.
14th.
I mentioned it to a bunch of your friends,
and nobody wanted to engage in the 14th.
Yeah.
Let's talk about the 14th Amendment.
Exactly.
The Citizenship Clause, which says that if you're born here,
you're a citizen of the United States.
Yes.
And I chose this because it's an extension
of the original debate and the immigration debate.
OK.
I think birthright citizenship, first of all,
when it was originally argued among the people who were
actually voting on the clause, it
was argued that the birthright citizenship was not
automatically extended to everybody
who was just born here.
And we have a long history of that as well,
for example, with the Native Americans,
who had particular laws that applied solely to them.
Yeah.
What I think we're seeing in this country
is not everybody is so similarly
under the jurisdiction thereof of the United States, right?
And by allowing for birthright citizenship
and not interpreting the Constitution
as we are legally allowed to and restrict
the automatic citizenship of anybody who's born here,
we actually remove the issue, for example,
of family separation.
Because there is no incentive of a family
to come over to this country illegally
and then have a child, which is contributing
to the awful situation we have in America of breaking up
families.
This is not something that I imagine you or I agree with.
No.
The issue is birthright citizenship
has incentivized that.
So even if I were to concede that in some cases
birthright citizenship has incentivized that,
I don't like the phrase anchor babies,
but I'm not naive enough to pretend
that there are not immigrants who come here
and time the pregnancy in order to get.
You and I can agree on that.
Yeah.
But that doesn't mean you then rip up
a constitutional principle that goes back centuries,
goes back before the 14th Amendment.
14th Amendment came about, I think, in 1868,
if memory serves me correctly.
But the principle underlying it is actually
from my other country, the UK, ancient English common law.
So this was always the case.
The 14th Amendment, as you know, because you seem well-read,
came along and codified what was already
a principle in American and English law
that if you're born in the country, you are a citizen.
Now, you mentioned the point about jurisdiction.
There is that little bit in there
where it says subject to the jurisdiction thereof.
That in the debate, if you go back and read the debate
that the senators had at the time,
they were very explicit that that
was to do with foreign ministers and foreign ambassadors.
Diplomats living in embassies, their kids
shouldn't be citizens.
Obviously, they're here on their own.
The Argentine embassy in DC is Argentine soil.
So we accept all that.
Absolutamente, amigo.
But when they were asked about Chinese immigrants,
Senator Trumbull, who was, I think,
the chair of the Judiciary Committee back in the 1860s
during this debate, he said at the time,
Chinese immigrants' children, they are citizens.
In fact, 1898, as you well know, we
get Wong Kim Ark, Supreme Court case, Wong Kim
Ark versus the United States.
And the Supreme Court says, yes, even
the child of undocumented Chinese immigrants
is an American citizen.
So this is a principle going back centuries.
So while I can agree with you that there
are cases that abuse the 14th Amendment,
that there are issues of family separation,
I'm not going to rip up a constitutional principle that
goes back centuries and is backed
by a 127-year-old Supreme Court president
because Donald Trump is looking for ways
to cut the number of brown and black people
in the United States.
If you don't mind me interrupting,
this is where I think it's important as well
to go back to what we talked about with the Constitution.
When we're analyzing, and admittedly, I'm
not as interested in the legal argument.
There's obviously many ways to interpret the Constitution.
But I don't think, especially among conservatives,
that it is positive to use the Constitution
to dismantle it.
When we analyze the original context,
like you were saying, in the late 19th century,
our immigration law was absolutely different,
including in respect with the Irish and Chinese immigrants
that were coming over.
It was absolutely different, changed.
We had open borders, my friend.
Some people in this room would hate it.
But hold on.
We had open borders for half of American history.
Well, I don't think that's very true.
It's 100% true.
Hold on.
If you're comparing the open borders, which I don't concede
to, but if you're comparing the open borders prior to 1910
and prior to the Hart-Cellar Act,
and you look at the amount of immigration,
and who was coming over.
Oh, nice deflection.
Amount is irrelevant.
We did have an open border.
It is absolutely relevant.
Why?
Because the Constitution, like the founding father.
So hold on.
Your argument is, we had open borders,
but there were fewer immigrants.
I was about to answer.
It's important to analyze the context wherein these laws
and parts of the Constitution arise.
The original founding father said,
the Constitution was made only for a moral and religious
people and is wholly inadequate to the government
of any other, which means the people that wrote this document
understood that it would not be able to properly
For secular people.
Let's just be clear on that.
Oh, no, that's not true.
They were deists.
A lot of them were super secular.
No, the majority were deists.
But they were secular.
Secular doesn't mean atheist.
You know what that means.
I understand that.
But deist doesn't mean secular or atheist.
It means they believe in a God, but not a God that's
particularly present.
I didn't say anything about whether they're deist or theist.
I said they're secular.
OK, but secular and deist.
It means you separate church and state.
OK, well, let's talk.
We could even talk about that.
That's a perfect example.
You're going to run out of your own time making your argument,
which you haven't made so far.
I understand.
But the separation of church and state
is now completely differently understood
than originally proposed.
Thomas Jefferson, who talks about the wall of separation,
which doesn't even exist in the Constitution,
understood it in a different way.
But it is a Supreme Court precedent, as you well know.
Yeah, sure.
But the precedent of the last 100 years, where
in the country has been completely
different from its founding, should not
overrule the original intent of the people who
wrote the document that you and I are both citing.
Which means.
But I'm not locked into what the people who wrote that.
We've had amendments to the Constitution.
You know that, right?
I understand that.
And this is our fundamental disagreement,
is that I don't believe.
You think you can read the minds of people in the 1770s.
That's not true.
And I'm stuck.
I just believe this country ought
to be more like the country we originally had.
And I don't think.
Great, that's your opinion.
And you're entitled to it.
I understand that.
But on a factual basis.
Well, let me try to see what you believe.
OK.
If we are voting on these constitutional amendments,
if we are interpreting them, and our interpretation becomes
absolutely, let's say, a 180 from what
the original intent of the authors of that document is,
are you in favor of that?